<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>

]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-zuniga-l2-addr-randomization-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
      <title abbrev="L2 addr randomization">
       Layer-2 address randomization
      </title>

    <!-- AUTHORS -->
    <author fullname="Juan Carlos Zuniga"
            initials="JC."
            surname="Zuniga">
      <organization abbrev="SIGFOX">
        SIGFOX
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>425 rue Jean Rostand</street>
          <city>Labege</city>
          <code> 31670</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>j.c.zuniga@ieee.org</email>
        <uri>http://www.sigfox.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos"
            initials="CJ."
            surname="Bernardos">
      <organization abbrev="UC3M">
        Universidad Carlos III de Madrid
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Universidad, 30</street>
          <city>Leganes, Madrid</city>
          <code>28911</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+34 91624 6236</phone>
        <email>cjbc@it.uc3m.es</email>
        <uri>http://www.it.uc3m.es/cjbc/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

<!-- CJBC: Amelia: please correct and complete below -->
    <author fullname="Amelia Andersdotter"
            initials="A."
            surname="Andersdotter">
      <organization abbrev="article19">
        article19
      </organization>
      <address>
        <email>amelia@article19.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2018" />

    <area>Internet</area>

<!--
    <workgroup>INTAREA</workgroup>
-->

    <abstract>

<!-- [2018-05-18] CJBC: Some initial text below. -->
      <t>
   Internet privacy has emerged as a serious concern.  Users' activities
   leave a vast digital footprint, communications are not always
   properly secured and a user's location can be easily tracked.  This document
   focuses on the use of IEEE Layer-2 immutable addresses, a leading cause of 
        geolocation tracking, and the implications of such tracking on upper layers, 
        specially on IPv6 addresses.  Randomization of the addresses used at Layer-2 
        is a simple, but promising, mitigation strategy for location privacy issues.
      </t>

      <t>
We report on existing support of address randomization by the different
operating systems, and also on the conclusions obtained from conducting several
trials during two IETF and one IEEE 802 standards meetings. Based on the
obtained results we can conclude that address randomization is a feasible
mitigation strategy for Layer-2 privacy problem, but that complementary mechanisms
are needed at higher layers to make the most benefit from it and minimize the service
disruptions it may cause.
      </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

<!-- BEGIN Terminology -->
    <section anchor="sec:introduction" title="Introduction">

<!-- [2018-05-18] CJBC: some initial text slightly modified from our paper to
use as starting point. -->
      <t>
The privacy of internet users has quickly become a huge concern, as more and more devices
are getting directly (e.g., via cellular or Wi-Fi) or indirectly (e.g., via a
smartphone using Bluetooth) connected to the Internet. This ubiquitous
connectivity, together with under-secured protocol stacks and a lack of
proper education about privacy, has made it easy to track and monitor the location
of users and/or eavesdrop their activity. This is due to many factors, such as
the vast digital footprint that users leave on the Internet (e.g., sharing
information on social networks, cookies used by browsers and servers to provide
a better navigation experience, connectivity logs that allow tracking of a
user’s Layer-2 (L2) or Layer-3 (L3) address, web trackers, etc.) and/or the weak
(or even null in some cases) authentication and encryption mechanisms used to
secure communications.
      </t>

      <t>
This privacy concern <xref target="wifi_internet_privacy" /> affects all layers
of the protocol stack, from the lower ones involved in the actual access to the
network (e.g., the Layer-2/Layer-3 addresses can be used to obtain the location
of a user) to the applications, especially when browsing or using social
networks (e.g., cookies can be used to find out the identity of a user accessing
a particular site).
      </t>

      <t>
This document focuses on the privacy threats at the network connectivity level,
namely at the Layer-2 and Layer-3 of the protocol stack, but focusing especially
on the issues related to the use of permanent Layer-2 addresses and the
potential advatages gained from randomizing them.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec:terminology" title="Terminology">

      <t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
      </t>

      <t>
The following terms are used in this document:

        <list style="empty">

          <t>XXX:</t>

          <t>YYY:</t>

        </list>

      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Terminology -->

<!-- BEGIN Problem statement -->
    <section anchor="sec:ps" title="Problem statement">

        <t>
        The issue of uniquely identifying individuals through their Layer-2 addresses was originally covered
          in vehicular communications research, where concerns about the
          disclosure of a driver's physical location were especially pronounced <xref target="buttyan2007" />.
          Because many of the promised advantages of vehicular communications relied upon drivers being
          comfortable with disclosing their location at regular intervals, pseudonymisation through regular
          changes of Layer-2 addresses was discussed as a privacy enhancing feature as far back as 2007.
        </t>
      <t>
        Using Layer-2 addresses to uniquely identify individuals later came to be covered in less specialised
        circumstances, such as in <xref target="cunche2013" />. There it is shown that even a passive observer using
        cheap tools can accurately pin down individual users of connected devices under relatively few constraints.
      </t>
      <t>
        By 2014 the ubiquity of public WLANs had led to the emergence of a number of new audience
        measurement models which attracted regulatory attention, particularly in the European Union. While under
        already existing EU norms, network operators were seen as being in a considerable position of power in 
        relation to the end-user, therefore carrying a special duty not to collect, store or use data about the 
        geographical location of an end-user without his or her informed consent, it had not been clarified at this
        point that similar obligations would extend to providers of local area networks and derived services too.
        However, both the Swedish Data Protection Authority and the Dutch Data Protection Authority would go on to issue injunctions
        against non-consensual collection of Layer-2 addresses from end-user devices (<xref target="di2015" />, 
        <xref target="ap2015" />), on the justification that end-users have the right to geolocational privacy. 
      </t>
      <t>
        While later research efforts have proceeded to demonstrate a range of other effective tracking mechanisms
        against users of wireless local area networks (see e.g. <xref target="matte2016" />, <xref target="vanhoef2016" /> and
        <xref target="martin2017" />), we do not believe this should distract from solutions to the Layer-2 addresses problem.
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Problem statement -->

<!-- BEGIN L2 address randomization -->
    <section anchor="sec:l2_addr_random" title="Layer-2 address randomization">

      <t>
The first serious attempt at addressing the issue of persistent Layer-2 addresses was seen in <xref target="ieee_1609.4_2010" />, which 
        supposes readressing, or resetting the device MAC address to a new value, in support of
        pseudonymity as an optional feature. In vehicular communications, privacy protections go even further
        by proposing higher level addresses, such as IP addresses, are also changed after some time.
      </t>
      <t>
        Later efforts include the introduction of Layer-2 addresses 
        randomisation feature in mobile operation systems, starting in 2014. While implementation is patchy, and
        not all mobile operating systems have this privacy protection mechanism turned on by default, in theory
        the vast majority of mobile operating system users around the world have an opportunity to increase their
        privacy protection by finding the right setting in their management interface.
      <t>By 2017, the IEEE 802 LMSC had started work on a built-in 802.11 network MAC randomization feature. 
        It was adopted as a standard in June 2018 <xref target="ieee_802.11aq" />, and pending approval by the 
        Wi-Fi Alliance may be shipped as a built-in privacy-enhancing feature in future generations of WiFi chips.
      </t>
      <t>
        In associations where private persons are directly interfacing a network provider, such as
        when they are connected through a personal device like a phone or laptop, it is likely that many different 
        options for Layer-2 addresses randomization will be available for the private person, at least if they remain unassociated.
      </t>
      <t>
        In other situations, where private persons are interacting with IoT devices (cars, etc), it is more
        likely that they will remain dependent on the properly implemented built-in privacy mechanisms.
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END L2 address randomization -->

<!-- BEGIN Tools -->
    <section anchor="sec:tools" title="Tools">

      <t>
TBD
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Tools -->

<!-- BEGIN Evaluation -->
    <section anchor="sec:eval" title="Evaluation">

      <t>
Layer-2 addresses randomization, or the alteration of the Layer-2 addresses at irregular intervals, is 
        recognised as a data minimization technique [RFC6973]. Though a number of research efforts have 
        proceeded to demonstrate a range of other effective tracking mechanisms
        against users of wireless local area networks (see e.g. <xref target="matte2016" />, 
        <xref target="vanhoef2016" /> ), we do not believe this should distract from solutions 
        to the Layer-2 addresses problem. It has further been proposed that in spite of Layer-2 address randomization
        mechanisms being implemented, they are often not used or are implemented in such a way 
        that the randomization is effective <xref target="martin2017" />.
      </t>
      <t>
        This suggests a continued need for improvement, and the recently adopted 802.11 enhancements may be
        helpful in this regard.
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Evaluation -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
N/A.
      </t>

    </section>


    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>
TBD.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">

      <t>
TBD.
      </t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc6973;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
       
      
      <reference anchor="martin2017" >
        <front>
          <title>A Study of MAC Address Randomization in Mobile Devices and When it Fails</title>
           <author initials="JM." surname="Marin" fullname="Jeremy Martin"></author>
           <author initials="TM." surname="Mayberry" fullname="Trevis Mayberry"></author>
           <author initials="CD." surname="Donahue" fullname="Collin Donahue"></author>
           <author initials="LF." surname="Foppe" fullname="Lucas Foppe"></author>
           <author initials="LB." surname="Brown" fullname="Lamont Brown"></author>
           <author initials="CR." surname="Riggins" fullname="Chadwick Riggins"></author>
           <author initials="ECR." surname="Rye" fullname="Erik C. Rye"></author>
           <author initials="DB." surname="Brown" fullname="Dane Brown"></author>
          <date month="March" year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="arxiv1703.02874" value="" />
      </reference>
                  
      <reference anchor="ap2015" >
        <front>
          <title>Wifi-tracking van mobiele apparaten in en rond winkels door Bluetrace</title>
          <author fullname="College Bescherming Persoongegevens"></author>
          <date month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Autoriteit Persoongegevens, z2014-00944." value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="buttyan2007" >
        <front>
          <title>On the Effectiveness of Changing Pseudonyms to Provide Location Privacy in VANETs</title>
          <author initials="LB." surname="Buttyán" fullname="Levente Buttyán"></author>
          <author initials="TH." surname="Holczer" fullname="Tamás Holczer"></author>
          <author initials="IV." surname="Vajda" fullname="István Bajda"></author>
          <date month="July" year="2007"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="(SEVECOM) in F. Stajano et al. (Eds.): ESAS 2007, LNCS 4572, pp. 129–141, 2007." value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="cunche2013" >
        <front>
          <title>I know your MAC Address: Targeted tracking of individual using Wi-Fi</title>
          <author initials="MC." surname="Cunche" fullname="Mathieu Cunche"></author>
          <date month="October" year="2013"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name=" International Symposium on Research in Grey-Hat Hacking - GreHack, Nov 2013, Grenoble, France. 2013." value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="di2015" >
        <front>
          <title>Tillsyn enligt personuppgiftslagen (1998:204) av Västerås Citysamverkan AB</title>
          <author fullname="Datainspektionen"></author>
          <date month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Datainspektionen Dnr 1702-2015." value="" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="ieee_1609.4_10" >
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Wireless Access in Vehicular Environments (WAVE)— Multi-channel Operation</title>
          <date month="February" year="2011"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Std 1609.4-2010" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ieee_802.11aq" >
        <front>
          <title>Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications. 
            Amendment 3: Pre-Association Discovery (still unpublished)</title>
          <date month="June" year="2018"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Std 802.11aq" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="matte2016" >
        <front>
          <title>Defeating MAC Address Randomization Through Timing Attacks</title>
          <author initials="CM." surname="Matte" fullname="Célestin Matte"></author>
          <author initials="MC." surname="Cunche" fullname="Mathieu Cunche"></author>
          <author initials="FR." surname="Rousseau" fullname="Franck Rosseau"></author>
          <author initials="MV." surname="Cunche" fullname="Mathy Vanhoef"></author>
          <date month="July" year="2016"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="WiSec’16, July 18-22, 2016, Darmstadt, Germany." value="" />
      </reference>
    
      <reference anchor="vanhoef2016" >
        <front>
          <title>Why MAC Address Randomization is not Enough: An Analysis of Wi-Fi Network Discovery Mechanisms</title>
          <author initials="MV." surname="Cunche" fullname="Mathy Vanhoef"></author>
          <author initials="CM." surname="Matte" fullname="Célestin Matte"></author>
          <author initials="MC." surname="Cunche" fullname="Mathieu Cunche"></author>
          <author initials="LSC." surname="Cardoso" fullname="Leonardo S. Cardoso"></author>
          <author initials="FP." surname="Piessens" fullname="Frank Piessens"></author>
          <date month="May" year="2016"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ASIA CCS ’16, May 30-June 03, 2016, Xi’an, China." value="" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="wifi_internet_privacy" >
        <front>
          <title>Wi-Fi Internet Connectivity and Privacy: Hiding your tracks on the wireless Internet</title>
          <author initials="CJ." surname="Bernardos" fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos">
          </author>
          <author initials="JC." surname="Zúñiga" fullname="Juan C. Zúñiga">
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="O'Hanlon" fullname="Piers O'Hanlon">
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Standards for Communications and Networking (CSCN), 2015 IEEE Conference on" value="" />
      </reference>

    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
