<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4862 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4191 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4191.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc7217 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7217.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dhc-mac-assign SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-mac-assign.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dhc-slap-quadrant SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-slap-quadrant.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc7844 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7844.xml'>

]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-zuniga-mac-address-randomization-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
      <title abbrev="MAC address randomization">
       MAC address randomization
      </title>

    <!-- AUTHORS -->
    <author fullname="Juan Carlos Zuniga"
            initials="JC."
            surname="Zuniga">
      <organization abbrev="SELF">
        SIGFOX
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>425 rue Jean Rostand</street>
          <city>Labege</city>
          <code> 31670</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>j.c.zuniga@ieee.org</email>
        <uri>http://www.sigfox.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos"
            initials="CJ."
            surname="Bernardos">
      <organization abbrev="UC3M">
        Universidad Carlos III de Madrid
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Universidad, 30</street>
          <city>Leganes, Madrid</city>
          <code>28911</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+34 91624 6236</phone>
        <email>cjbc@it.uc3m.es</email>
        <uri>http://www.it.uc3m.es/cjbc/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

<!-- Amelia: please correct and complete below -->
    <author fullname="Amelia Andersdotter"
            initials="A."
            surname="Andersdotter">
      <organization abbrev="article19">
        article19
      </organization>
      <address>
        <email>amelia@article19.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2020" />

    <area>Internet</area>

<!--
    <workgroup>INTAREA</workgroup>
-->

    <abstract>

      <t>
Internet privacy has become a major concern over the past few years.  
Users are becoming more aware that their online activity  leaves a vast digital footprint, 
that communications are not always properly secured, and that their location and actions 
can be easily tracked. One of the main factors for the location tracking issue is the 
wide use of long-lasting identifiers, such as MAC addresses. 

      </t>

      <t>
There have been several initiatives at the IETF and the IEEE 802 standards committees to 
overcome some of these privacy issues. This document provides an overview of these activities, 
with the intention to inform the technical community about them, and help coordinate between 
present and futures standardization activities.
      </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

<!-- BEGIN Terminology -->
    <section anchor="sec:introduction" title="Introduction">

<!-- [2018-05-18] CJBC: some initial text slightly modified from our paper to
use as starting point. -->
      <t>
Internet privacy is becoming a huge concern, as more and more mobile devices
are getting directly (e.g., via cellular or Wi-Fi) or indirectly (e.g., via a
smartphone using Bluetooth) connected to the Internet. This ubiquitous
connectivity, together with not very secure protocol stacks and the lack of
proper education about privacy make it very easy to track/monitor the location
of users and/or eavesdrop their physical and online activities. This is due to many factors, such as
the vast digital footprint that users leave on the Internet, for instance sharing
information on social networks, cookies used by browsers and servers to provide
a better navigation experience, connectivity logs that allow tracking of a
user’s Layer-2 (L2/MAC) or Layer-3 (L3) address, web trackers, etc.; and/or the weak
(or even null in some cases) authentication and encryption mechanisms used to
secure communications.
      </t>

      <t>
This privacy concern affects all layers of the protocol stack, from the lower layers 
involved in the actual access to the network (e.g., the MAC/Layer-2 and Layer-3 addresses 
can be used to obtain the location of a user) to higher layer protocol identifiers and 
user applications <xref target="wifi_internet_privacy" />. In particular, IEEE 802 MAC 
addresses have historically been an easy target for tracking users [REF to some tracking cases].
      </t>

      <t>
There have been several initiatives at the IETF and the IEEE 802 standards committees 
to overcome some of these privacy issues. This document provides an overview of these 
activities, with the intention to inform the community and help coordinate between 
present and futures standardization activities.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec:terminology" title="Terminology">

      <t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
      </t>

      <t>
The following terms are used in this document:

        <list style="empty">

          <t>MAC: Medium Access Control</t>

        </list>

      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Terminology -->

<!-- BEGIN Problem statement -->
    <section anchor="sec:background" title="Background – MAC address usage">

        <t>
Most mobile devices used today are Wi-Fi enabled (i.e. they are equipped with an 
IEEE 802.11 wireless interface). Wi-Fi interfaces, as any other kind of IEEE 802-based 
network interface, like Ethernet (i.e. IEEE 802.3) have a Layer-2 address also referred 
to as MAC address, which can be seen by anybody who can receive the signal transmitted by 
the network interface. The format of these addresses is shown in Figure 1. 
        </t>

        <t>
		Figure 1: IEEE 802 MAC Address Format
        </t>		


        <t>
MAC addresses can either be universally administered or locally administered. Universally 
administered and locally administered addresses are distinguished by setting the 
second-least-significant bit of the most significant byte of the address (the U/L bit).
        </t>

        <t>
A universally administered address is uniquely assigned to a device by its manufacturer. 
Most physical devices are provided with a universally administered address, which is composed 
of two parts: (i) the Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI), which are the first 
three octets in transmission order and identify the organization that issued the identifier, 
and (ii) Network Interface Controller (NIC) Specific, which are the following three octets, 
assigned by the organization that manufactured the NIC, in such a way that the resulting 
MAC address is globally unique. 
        </t>
		
		<t>
Locally administered addresses override the burned-in address, and they are usually set-up 
by the network administrator. However, as explained in further sections of this document, 
there are new initiatives at the IEEE 802 to specify ways in which these locally administered 
addresses should be assigned, depending on the use case.		
        </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Problem statement -->

<!-- BEGIN MAC address randomization -->
    <section anchor="sec:mac_addr_random" title="MAC address randomization">

      <t>
Since universally administered MAC addresses are by definition globally-unique, when a device 
uses this MAC address to transmit data -especially over the air- it is relatively easy to track 
this device by simple medium observation. Since a device is usually directly associated to an 
individual, this poses a privacy concern <xref target="link_layer_privacy" />.
      </t>

      <t>
MAC addresses can be easily observed by a third party, such as a passive device listening to 
communications in the same network. In an 802.11 network, a station exposes its MAC address in 
two different situations:	  
      </t>

<t><list style="symbols">
	  <t>
While actively scanning for available networks, the MAC address is used in the Probe Request 
frames sent by the device (aka IEEE 802.11 STA).
      </t>
	  
	  <t>
Once associated to a given Access Point (AP), the MAC address is used in frame transmission and 
reception, as one of the addresses used in the address fields of an IEEE 802.11 frame.
      </t>
</list></t>
	  
	  <t>
One way to overcome this privacy concern is by using randomly generated MAC addresses. 
As described in the previous section, the IEEE 802 addressing includes one bit to specify if the 
hardware address is locally or globally administered. This allows generating local addresses 
without the need of any global coordination mechanism to ensure that the generated address is unique.
This feature can be used to generate random addresses <xref target="enhancing_location_privacy" />, and therefore makes it more difficult 
to track a user device from its MAC/L2 address. 
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec:mac_addr_experiments" title="Experiments at IETF and IEEE 802 meetings">	  
	  <t>
In order to test the effects of MAC address randomization, major trials were conducted at the 
IETF and IEEE 802 meetings between November 2014 and March 2015 - IETF91, IETF92 and IEEE 802 Plenary in Berlin. 
The purpose of the experiments was to evaluate the use of MAC address randomization from two 
different perspectives: (i) the effect on the connectivity experience of the end-user, also checking 
if applications and operating systems (OSs) were affected; and (ii) the potential impact on the 
network infrastructure itself. Some of the findings were published in <xref target="wifi_internet_privacy" />. 
      </t>

      <t>
During the experiments it was observed that the probability of address duplication in a network with this characteristics is negligible. 
The experiments also showed that other protocol identifiers can be correlated and therefore be used to still track an individual. Hence, 
effective privacy tools should not work in isolation at a single layer, but they should be coordinated with other privacy features at higher layers. 
Since then, the MAC address randomization feature has been used every time by more devices and operating systems [REF??]. 	  
	  </t>

	  
    </section>
<!-- END L2 address randomization -->

<!-- BEGIN Tools -->
    <section anchor="sec:mac_rnd_at_ieee802" title="MAC randomization-related activities at the IEEE 802">

      <t>
(From IEEE 802.11aq...)
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Tools -->

<!-- BEGIN Evaluation -->
    <section anchor="sec:mac_rnd_at_ietf" title="MAC randomization-related activities at the IETF">

      <t>
Several IP address assignment mechanisms such as the IPv6 stateless
autoconfiguration techniques (SLAAC) <xref target="RFC4862" /> generate the
Interface Identifier (IID) of the address from its MAC address (via EUI64),
which then becomes visible to all IPv6 communication peers. This potentially
allows for global tracking of a device at L3 from any point on the Internet.
Besides, the prefix part of the address provides meaningful insights of the
physical location of the device in general, which together with the MAC
address-based IID, makes it easier to perform global device tracking.
      </t>

      <t>
There are some solutions that might mitigate this privacy threat, such as the
use of temporary addresses <xref target="RFC4191" />, the use of opaque IIDs
<xref target="RFC7217" />, <xref
target="I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses" />. Next, we briefly
describe how these solutions work.
      </t>

      <t>
<xref target="RFC4191" /> identifies and describes the privacy issues associated
with embedding MAC stable addressing information into the IPv6 addresses (as
part of the IID) and describes some mechanisms to mitigate the associated
problems. The specification is meant for IPv6 nodes that auto-configure IPv6
addresses based on the MAC address (EUI-64 mechanism). It defines how to create
additional addresses (generally known as "temporary addresses") based on a
random interface identifier for the purpose of initiating outgoing sessions.
These "random" or temporary addresses are meant to be used for a short period of
time (hours to days) and would then be deprecated. Deprecated addresses can
continue to be used for already established connections, but are not used to
initiate new connections. New temporary addresses are generated periodically to
replace temporary addresses that expire. In order to do so, a node produces a
sequence of temporary global scope addresses from a sequence of interface
identifiers that appear to be random in the sense that it is difficult for an
outside observer to predict a future address (or identifier) based on a current
one, and it is difficult to determine previous addresses (or identifiers)
knowing only the present one. The main problem with the temporary addresses is
that they should not be used by applications that listen for incoming
connections (as these are supposed to be waiting on permanent/well-known
identifiers). Besides, if a node changes network and comes back to a previously
visited one, the temporary addresses that the node would use will be different,
and this might be an issue in certain networks where addresses are used for
operational purposes (e.g., filtering or authentication). <xref target="RFC7217"
/>, summarized next, partially addresses the problems aforementioned.
      </t>

      <t>
<xref target="RFC7217"/> defines a method for generating IPv6 IIDs to be used
with IPv6 Stateless Address Autoconfiguration (SLAAC), such that an IPv6 address
configured using this method is stable within each subnet, but the corresponding
IID changes when the host moves from one network to another. This method is
meant to be an alternative to generating Interface Identifiers based on MAC
addresses, such that the benefits of stable addresses can be achieved without
sacrificing the security and privacy of users. The method defined to generate
the IPv6 IID is based on computing a hash function which takes as input
information that is stable and associated to the interface (e.g., MAC address or
local interface identifier), stable information associated to the visited
network (e.g., IEEE 802.11 SSID), the IPv6 prefix, and a secret key, plus some
other additional information. This basically ensures that a different IID is
generated when any of the input fields changes (such as the network or the
prefix), but that the IID is the same within each subnet.
      </t>

      <t>
In addition to the former documents, <xref target="I-D.ietf-dhc-mac-assign" />
proposes an extension to DHCPv6 that allows a scalable approach to link-layer
address assignments where preassigned link-layer address assignments (such as by
a manufacturer) are not possible or unnecessary. <xref
target="I-D.ietf-dhc-slap-quadrant" /> proposes extensions to DHCPv6 protocols
to enable a DHCPv6 client or a DHCPv6 relay to indicate a preferred SLAP
quadrant to the server, so that the server may allocate MAC addresses in the
quadrant requested by the relay or client.
      </t>

      <t>
Not only MAC and IP addresses can be used for tracking purposes. Some DHCP
options carry unique identifiers. These identifiers can enable device tracking
even if the device administrator takes care of randomizing other potential
identifications like link-layer addresses or IPv6 addresses. <xref
target="RFC7844" /> introduces anonymity profiles, designed for clients that
wish to remain anonymous to the visited network. The profiles provide guidelines
on the composition of DHCP or DHCPv6 messages, designed to minimize disclosure
of identifying information. <xref target="RFC7844" /> also indicates that the
link-layer address, IP address, and DHCP identifier shall evolve in synchrony.
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Evaluation -->


    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
N/A.
      </t>

    </section>


    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>
TBD.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">

      <t>
TBD.
      </t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &rfc4862;
      &rfc4191;
      &rfc7217;
      &I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses;
      &I-D.ietf-dhc-mac-assign;
      &I-D.ietf-dhc-slap-quadrant;
      &rfc7844;

      <reference anchor="wifi_internet_privacy" >
        <front>
          <title>Wi-Fi Internet Connectivity and Privacy: Hiding your tracks on the wireless Internet</title>
          <author initials="CJ." surname="Bernardos" fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos">
          </author>
          <author initials="JC." surname="Zúñiga" fullname="Juan C. Zúñiga">
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="O'Hanlon" fullname="Piers O'Hanlon">
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Standards for Communications and Networking (CSCN), 2015 IEEE Conference on" value="" />
      </reference>
	  
      <reference anchor="link_layer_privacy" >
        <front>
          <title>Privacy at the link layer</title>
           <author initials="P." surname="O'Hanlon" fullname="Piers O'Hanlon">
          </author>
		  <author initials="J." surname="Wright" fullname="J. Wright">
          </author>
          <author initials="I." surname="Brown" fullname="Ian Brown">
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2014"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Contribution at W3C/IAB workshop on Strengthening the Internet Against Pervasive Monitoring (STRINT)" value="" />
      </reference> 
	  

      <reference anchor="enhancing_location_privacy" >
        <front>
          <title>Enhancing location privacy in wireless LAN through disposable interface identifiers: a quantitative analysis</title>
           <author initials="M." surname="Gruteser" fullname="M. Gruteser">
          </author>
		  <author initials="D." surname="Grunwald" fullname="D. Grunwald">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Mobile Networks and Applications, vol. 10, no. 3, pp. 315–325" value="" />
      </reference> 


    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
